Guide to the Nathan Salsbury Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nathan Salsbury papers
1860-1965
1866-1903
YCAL MSS 17
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.96
(6 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, writings and photographs on the life and career of Nate Salsbury.
Salsbury, Nathan, 1846-1902
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Rebecca Salsbury James and Rachel Salsbury Schloss, 1964-67.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 6: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Nathan Salsbury, Objects Associated with Buffalo Bill (WA MSS S-3019), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
NATHAN SALSBURY (1846-1902)
Nathan Salsbury, son of Nathan and Rebecca Welch Salsbury, was born in Freeport, Illinois. Left an orphan, he lived with his stepfather, Jedutha Fuller. On the outbreak of the Civil War, he enlisted in the ranks of the Union Army. He served in the 89th and 59th Illinois regiments in the Army of the Cumberland and was wounded three times. After discharge Salsbury became an actor and wrote several plays, including "Patchwork" and "On the Trail, or, Money and Misery." In 1875 he organized Salsbury's Troubadours, a successful acting company, and in 1884 joined Buffalo Bill as co-owner of Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show. Eleven years later he established "Black America," an acting, singing, and tumbling extravaganza with a cast of 600 African Americans.
Salsbury married Rachel Samuels, a young actress, in 1887. The couple had four children, one of whom was Rebecca Salsbury James. Nate Salsbury died on December 24, 1902 in Long Branch, New Jersey.
For additional biographical information, see The National Cyclopaedia of American Biography, Vol. VIII, page 166, and his "Reminiscences" (Box 2, folders 62-63).
SALSBURY FAMILY
Nathan Salsbury (1780- ) m. Lemira Clark (1788- )
Nathan Salsbury ( -1847?) m. Rebecca Welch* ( -1854?)
Nathan Salsbury (1846-1902) m. 1887 Rachel Samuels (1856- )
Nathan Salsbury (1888-1963)
Milton S. Salsbury (1890-
Rachel Salsbury (1891- ) m. William H. Schloss
Rebecca Salsbury (1891-1968) m. 1 Paul Strand (1890-1976) m. 2 William H. James (1899-1962)
Martha Salsbury m. Jedutha Fuller (1812?-
Washington C. Salsbury m. Celestina Rawson
Nathan Rawson Salsbury (1856- ) m 1881 Frances A Gibbs (1866- )
Mattie Salsbury m. Akeley
Lemira Salsbury m. 1847 Jessie C. Wells
Note: The first Nathan Salsbury had four other children. *Rebecca Welch later married Jedutha Fuller and after her death Fuller married Martha Salsbury.
Scope and Contents
The Nathan Salsbury Papers contain correspondence, personal papers, photographs, a scrapbook, and memorabilia documenting the life and career of Nate Salsbury, nineteenth-century actor and co-owner of Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show. The papers span the dates 1860-1965, but the bulk of the material covers the years 1866-1903.
Series I, Correspondence, consist of eighteen folders of chronologically arranged correspondence. The two earliest letters were written by Nate Salsbury in 1860-61. In them he alludes to running away from his stepfather and to his interest in joining the circus. These are followed by nine letters from Harriet C. Fuller, Nate's teen-age half-sister, written between 1866-70. Also included in the correspondence are letters from Salsbury relatives and friends which mention his acting career. Some useful information concerning Nate's long association with William F. Cody and the Buffalo Bill Wild West Show can also be found. The collection contains nine letters from Buffalo Bill and additional letters from J. A. Bailey, John M. Burke, Jack Crawford, Jules Keen, and Steele MacKaye concerning the Show. In his reminiscences (Box 2, folder 63), Salsbury stated that when he wrote his famous book, its title was going to be "Sixteen Years in Hell with Buffalo Bill." Cody, was in his opinion, a dishonest drunkard whose only loyalty was to his incompetent cronies. Buffalo Bill's drinking problem is discussed several times throughout the papers. In Cody's first letter to Salsbury, probably written in 1884, he vowed "that after this you will never see me under the influence of liquor," although he added, "I may have to take two or three drinks to day to brace up." In a 1907 letter to Rachel Salsbury, Jack Crawford asserted that Buffalo Bill was "not a Square dealer" and that "Ned Buntline created the most selfish and brutal faker... ever perpetrated on the American People." The collection also includes invitations and requests for tickets, most dating from the time of the Wild West Show's tours of Great Britain in 1887 and 1892.
For the period between 1891 and Salsbury's death in December 1902, there is a small series of letters between Salsbury and his wife, Rachel, and sons, Nate, Jr. and Milton. Other correspondents include David J. Burrell, Kate Field, General Nelson A. Miles, Milton E. Milner, Frederic Remington, and Bram Stoker. Correspondence dating from after Salsbury's death discusses the sale of Salsbury's stock in the Buffalo Bill Show, other estate matters, the disposition of artifacts he collected, and reminiscences about Nate Salsbury and Buffalo Bill. In a 1924 letter, for example, Frank Butler, husband of Annie Oakley, refers to Salsbury "as one of the whitest men" he had ever known.
Series II, Personal Papers, are found in Boxes 1-2, folders 19-64. Included are biographical information, memorabilia on Buffalo Bill's Wild West, invitations and programs, printed works, papers on Salsbury's Troubadours, and writings of Nate Salsbury. The Buffalo Bill folders contain copies of the 1887 articles of incorporation, invitations, programs, and schedules. The printed works section offers some useful information on Salsbury's Troubadours and the Wild West Show. A great deal of additional Wild West Show material is found in the scrapbook (Box 5, folder 106). Writings include the original manuscript for an 1871 play, "On the Trail; or, Money and Misery" together with a number of poems, perhaps used in stage performances; an 1865 poem written by Salsbury; and a series of reminiscences written in 1901 or 1902. The reminiscences contain anecdotes and stories of his Civil War experiences, Salsbury's Troubadours, the founding of the Wild West Show, and pungent observations on Buffalo Bill. One Civil War anecdote featuring General William T. Sherman is particularly interesting. Other personal papers include Civil War discharge papers; poetic tributes to Salsbury and Buffalo Bill; recitations dating from Salsbury's acting days; a brochure for "The Reservation," cottages in Long Beach, New Jersey owned and rented by Salsbury; and a posthumous tribute by David J. Burrell.
Series III, Photographs, predominately family and friends are housed in Boxes 2-3, folders 65-89. Many of the pictures of Nate Salsbury and Rachel Samuels Salsbury date from the period when both were on the stage. In addition, the photographs contain thirty stereoscopic views of the Wild West Show (Box 4, folders 90-97) sold by Underwood & Underwood. A small Memorabilia series includes three jubilee coins of Great Britain, two medals, and a paperweight.
The collection concludes with one box of Oversize papers. The most significant item in the section is a large scrapbook which houses letters, invitations, menus, tickets, Wild West Show memorabilia, newspaper clippings, programs, broadsides, and other like papers. Much of the material found elsewhere in the Salsbury Papers was removed from the scrapbook. The letters include such items as a dinner invitation from Frederic Remington, a short August 1888 letter from Albert Bierstadt, a June 6, 1888 letter from Steele MacKaye congratulating Salsbury on the birth of a son, and an 1888 letter from Henry Watterson on the stationery of the "Headquarters National Democratic Committee." Other items of interest include a May 22, 1873 special order of Abraham Lincoln Post 11 GAR appointing Salsbury one of six company commanders; German, Spanish, and Italian programs for the Wild West Show; publicity for Salsbury's Troubadours; and a December 29, 1865 open letter from Brevet Brigadier General P. Sidney Post to the soldiers of the 59th Regiment of the Illinois Volunteer Infantry congratulating them for their outstanding war service.
Musicals; Playwriting; Revues; Wild west shows; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Anecdotes; Photographs -- United States -- 19th century; Reminiscences; Stereographs -- United States -- 19th century; Tintypes (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Actors -- United States -- 19th century; Theatrical managers -- United States -- 19th century; Buffalo Bill, 1846-1917; Fuller, Hattie C.; Salsbury, Nathan, 1846-1902; Salsbury, Rachel Samuels; Salisbury family; Buffalo Bill's Wild West Company; Salsbury's Troubadours
- Correspondence, 1860-66; Series I
  - Correspondence, 1860-66 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1868-69 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1870-78 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1883-86 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1888-89 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1890-93 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1894-95 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1897-98 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1902-03 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1904-13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1924-65 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C-S, unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
- Personal Papers, n.d.; Series II
  - Autograph signatures, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Biographical information, 1881-1936, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Oversize, Box 5, folder 102
  - "Black America:" broadside, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Buffalo Bill's Wild West
    - Articles of incorporation, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Invitations and tickets, 1892-1900, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letterheads, 1884-1902, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Menus, 1887-1902 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Papers, 1887, 1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Programs, 1887, 1889, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Schedules, 1906, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Civil War
    - Records, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Widow's pension, 1909, 1920, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition labels, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Invitations and programs, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Invitations, passes, and calling cards, 1885-97, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1886, 1896, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Menus, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Organizations
    - 89th Illinois Infantry Reunion Association, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - The Fellowship Club, 1893, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Grand Army of the Republic, 1869-90, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - The Lambs, 1888-1902, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous, 1882, 1894, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Passenger list for the Ems, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Passport
    See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 103
  - Poetry: tributes to Salsbury and Buffalo Bill, 1882-1905 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Printed Works
    See also: Oversize, Box 5, folder 104
    - Denver Public Library, Western History Collection: Its Beginning and Growth, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - James, Rebecca Salsbury, Allow Me to Present, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Nate Salsbury and the beginnings of musical comedy, 1947-48 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "Nate Salsbury and the Wild West Show," Colorado Magazine, 1955 Jul (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Newspaper clippings about Buffalo Bill, 1939-67 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Newspaper report of volcano eruption on Martinique, 1902 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Program: "Indian Days in Texas", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Souvenir of the National Frontiersmen's Association, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Programs, 1887-97, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Recitations, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - The Reservation: brochure, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Salsbury family genealogical notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Salsbury's Troubadours, 1873-87, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
    See also: Oversize, Box 5, folder 105
  - Scrapbook
    See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 106
  - Sketch in pencil of unidentified man, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Tribute: "My Showman Friend" by David James Burrell, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Writings
    - Copyright for "The Sanguinary Chasm", 1879 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "On the Trail, or, Money and Misery", 1871 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Poetry: "Veterans Growl", 1865 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Reminiscences, ca. 1901 (Box 2, Folder 63-64)
- Photographs, n.d.; Series III
  - Aurora, Illinois Zouaves, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Buffalo Bill and General Nelson Miles, 1891
  - James, Rebecca Salsbury: includes pictures of Frieda Lawrence, Georgia O'Keeffe, and members of Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - McHenry, Nellie, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Milner, Milton E., 1905, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Rifle belonging to Nate Salsbury, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Salsbury family, 1897, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 70-73)
  - Salsbury, Milton S., 1918, 1921, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - [Empty folder] (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Salsbury, Nate, 1858-1901, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76-82)
  - Salsbury, Nathan Rawson, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Salsbury, Rachel Samuels, 1879-1915, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84-89)
  - Stereoscopic views: Buffalo Bill's Wild West, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90-97)
- Memorabilia, Series IV
  - Numismatic items
    - Great Britain: Jubilee three pence, six pence, and sovereign, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Spain: dos centavos, 1870
    - Aluminum token, one-sided, n.d.
    - Medal, brass: Land und Forstwirtschaftliche Ausstellung, Wien, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Medal, white metal: First National Convention of Cattlemen, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Paperweight containing picture of Nate Salsbury, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 101)
- Oversize, 1903
  - Biographical information: estate administration, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Passport, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Printed works: "Nym Crinkle's Feulleton", 1887 Feb 12 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Salsbury's Troubadours, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Scrapbook, 1865-1902 (Box 5, Folder 106)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 7, 8, 20, 21 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Box 2, folders 45, 48, 49, 53 (Box 6, Folder 108)